<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Wallace Lab</title>
    <description>We are the Wallace lab at King’s College London. We build artificial mimics of cell membranes; both to improve our understanding of membrane biology, and to engineer new devices inspired by biology.</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 17:17:03 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 17:17:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.4.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Orchestrating Self-Replication in Artificial Cells through Digital Microfluidics</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;DMF Replicator&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;DMF Replicator&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/DMF_replicator.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;DMF Replicator&lt;/span&gt;
A defining feature of living cells is their ability to self-replicate; but creating artificial cells with this capability remains challenging, due to the complexity of biological division machinery. Rather than seeking to reconstitute this machinery, here we take direct control of DNA replication and compartment division using digital microfluidics. This approach allows us to precisely orchestrate these two fundamental processes, providing insight into how they must be coupled for successful self-replication.
&lt;!--more--&gt;
 Our system achieves autonomous cycles of replication and division, with daughter compartments inheriting parental DNA and maintaining genetic continuity across multiple generations - a key feature of living systems that has been difficult to achieve in artificial cells. By implementing these processes through direct physical manipulation rather than biochemical complexity, we provide a simple testbed that will help to disentangle the essential requirements for self-replicating systems.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/25/Zhai_Biorxiv</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/25/Zhai_Biorxiv</guid>
        
        
        <category>papers</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Group Scientific Away Day in Brighton</title>
        <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/group/Brighton.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;maincolumn-figure&quot;&gt;Escaped from London and let loose on Brighton for a day of science and some fun.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/25/Brighton</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/25/Brighton</guid>
        
        <category>fun</category>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Triply Responsive Control of Anion/Cation Transport with an Artificial Ion Channel Responsive to Multiple Stimuli</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;azo-p5&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;azo-p5&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/Malla_2025.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;azo-p5 ion channels.&lt;/span&gt;
We present a synthetic ion channel whose activity can be controlled by three orthogonal stimuli (light, pH, guest/ligand). The channel is formed from a pillar[5]arene functionalized with photoswitchable tetrafluoroazobenzene moieties. We demonstrate excellent control over E:Z switching across ten incorporated photoswitches (E to Z 87%, Z to E quant.). We show that the most active isomer – the Z-isomer – forms dimeric ion channels in membranes, with selectivity for M+/Cl− symport. Single molecule planar bilayer conductance studies show distinct high and low conductance states dependent on irradiation wavelength. Finally, we demonstrate that this activity can be modulated over 170-fold by controlling pH, irradiation, and guest addition, creating a powerful addition to the canon of synthetic ion channels.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/25/Malla_ChemRxiv</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/25/Malla_ChemRxiv</guid>
        
        
        <category>papers</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Rational Design Principles for De Novo α-Helical Peptide Barrels with Dynamic Conductive Channels</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;aHB&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;aHB&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/Nitsu_2024.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;α-helical peptide channels.&lt;/span&gt;
Despite advances in peptide and protein design, the rational design of membrane-spanning peptides that form conducting channels remains challenging due to our imperfect understanding of the sequence-to-structure relationships that drive membrane insertion, assembly, and conductance. Here, we describe the design and computational and experimental characterization of a series of coiled coil-based peptides that form transmembrane α-helical barrels with conductive channels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through a combination of rational and computational design, we obtain barrels with 5 to 7 helices, as characterized in detergent micelles. In lipid bilayers, these peptide assemblies exhibit two conductance states with relative populations dependent on the applied potential: (i) low-conductance states that correlate with variations in the designed amino-acid sequences and modeled coiled-coil barrel geometries, indicating stable transmembrane α-helical barrels; and (ii) high-conductance states in which single channels change size in discrete steps. Notably, the high-conductance states are similar for all peptides in contrast to the low-conductance states. This indicates the formation of large, dynamic channels, as observed in natural barrel-stave peptide channels. These findings establish rational routes to design and tune functional membrane-spanning peptide channels with specific conductance and geometry. Published in JACS.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/25/Nitsu_NatComms</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/25/Nitsu_NatComms</guid>
        
        
        <category>papers</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Real-time label-free imaging of living crystallization-driven self-assembly</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;CDSA&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;CDSA&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/Guo_2024.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Real-time label-free imaging of living crystallization-driven self-assembly.&lt;/span&gt;
Our latest work now published in Nature Communications. This is the last of our pandemic papers, so no membrane biophysics! Applying label-free microscopy to watch polymer self-assembly in real-time. This lets us map directly how reaction parameters affect the composition and growth of individual 2D polymer microplatelets. A fantastic collaboration with Rachel O’Reilly at the University of Birmingham. Congratulations go to Yujie Guo for another fantastic bit of science.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/25/Guo_CDSA</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/25/Guo_CDSA</guid>
        
        
        <category>papers</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ion Transport and Membrane Channel Formation Using a Peptidomimetic in Droplet Interface Bilayers</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;CDSA&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;CDSA&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/TBP2.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Peptidomimetic channels.&lt;/span&gt;
Herein, we present a synthetic peptidomimetic, TBP2, which forms artificial membrane channels within Droplet Interface Bilayers (DIBs). Through real-time electrophysiology, TIRF microscopy, and single-channel recordings, we demonstrate the ability of TBP2 to mediate high-conductance transport of Na⁺ and K⁺ across the DIBs, highlighting its potential for
nanobiotechnology applications in cell-free systems.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/25/Paul_chemcomm</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/25/Paul_chemcomm</guid>
        
        
        <category>papers</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Siyuan Zhou</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot; Siyuan Zhou&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot; Siyuan Zhou&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/people/siyuan_zhou_mugshot.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Siyuan Zhou&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Siyuan joined the group as KURF student 2022 studying Biochemistry BSc at King’s, after come back from a exchange year at Hopkins, he finished his final year on the project ‘De novo Design of Ion Channels from α-Helical Barrels ‘ and continues his PhD on De novo protein channel design research as a BBSRC LIDo project student. Outside lab he is a reptile keeper and scuba diver.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/25/Siyuan</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/25/Siyuan</guid>
        
        
        <category>people</category>
        
        <category>current</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Christmas Dinner in Covent Garden</title>
        <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/Christmas_2024.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;maincolumn-figure&quot;&gt;Hotpot at Leicester Square and an early Christmas present from the group (I think&amp;#8230;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/24/Christmas-2</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/24/Christmas-2</guid>
        
        <category>fun</category>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>De novo design of α-helical peptide channels with designer stoichiometry</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;aHB&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;aHB&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/Nitsu_2024.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;α-helical peptide channels.&lt;/span&gt;
Despite advances in peptide and protein design, the rational design of membrane-spanning peptides that form conducting channels remains challenging due to our imperfect understanding of the sequence-to-structure relationships that drive membrane insertion, assembly, and conductance. Here, we describe the design and computational and experimental characterization of a series of coiled coil-based peptides that form transmembrane α-helical barrels.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/24/Nitsu_biorxiv</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/24/Nitsu_biorxiv</guid>
        
        
        <category>papers</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Adelina Krusteva</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;Adelina Krusteva&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;Adelina Krusteva&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/people/adelina_mugshot.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Adelina Krusteva&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adelina’s journey began during an industrial placement year at Ipsen, where she gained hands-on experience in protein engineering working with Botulinum toxins. After completing her BSc at King’s, she joined the Wallace lab to continue work on the translocation mechanism of BoNT. Outside the lab, she is a painter and a practitioner of BJJ and Muay Thai—pursuing these passions when inspiration and energy align.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/24/AdelinaKrusteva</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/24/AdelinaKrusteva</guid>
        
        
        <category>people</category>
        
        <category>current</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
