<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Wallace Lab</title>
    <description>We are the Wallace lab at King’s College London. We build artificial mimics of cell membranes; both to improve our understanding of membrane biology, and to engineer new devices inspired by biology.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 15:34:06 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 15:34:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Zhongdao Li</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;ZhongDaoLi&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;ZhongDaoLi&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/people/zhongdao_mugshot.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Zhongdao Li&lt;/span&gt;
After a KURF summer studentship failed to dissuade Zhongdao from working in the lab he joins us for a PhD working on new methods to link artificial cells and real cells.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 30 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/articles/21/ZhongdaoLi</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/articles/21/ZhongdaoLi</guid>
        
        
        <category>people</category>
        
        <category>current</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Guanzhong Zhai</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;YujieGuo&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;YujieGuo&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/people/guanzhong_mugshot.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Guanzong Zhai&lt;/span&gt;
Supported by the King’s-China Scholarship Council PhD Scholarship programme (K-CSC), Guanzhong Zhai joins the Wallace group working on on new methods for artificial cell fabrication.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 29 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/articles/21/GuanzhongZhai</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/articles/21/GuanzhongZhai</guid>
        
        
        <category>people</category>
        
        <category>current</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Constructing ion channels from water-soluble alpha-helical barrels</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;peptidebarrels.jpg&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;peptidebarrels.jpg&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/peptidebarrels.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Designer alpha-helical barrels.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design of peptides that assemble in membranes to form functional ion channels is challenging. Specifically, hydrophobic interactions must be designed between the peptides and at the peptide–lipid interfaces simultaneously. Here, we take a multi-step approach towards this problem. First, we use rational de novo design to generate water-soluble α-helical barrels with polar interiors, and confirm their structures using high-resolution X-ray crystallography. These α-helical barrels have water-filled lumens like those of transmembrane channels. Next, we modify the sequences to facilitate their insertion into lipid bilayers. Single-channel electrical recordings and fluorescent imaging of the peptides in membranes show monodisperse, cation-selective channels of unitary conductance.
&lt;!--more--&gt;
Surprisingly, however, an X-ray structure solved from the lipidic cubic phase for one peptide reveals an alternative state with tightly packed helices and a constricted channel. To reconcile these observations, we perform computational analyses to compare the properties of possible different states of the peptide.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 10 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/articles/21/Scott-NatChem</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/articles/21/Scott-NatChem</guid>
        
        
        <category>papers</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Single-molecule imaging of pore-forming toxin dynamics in droplet interface bilayers</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;methods.gif&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;methods.gif&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/methods.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Our chapter in Methods 619.&lt;/span&gt;
Single-channel recording from pore-forming toxins (PFTs) provides a clear and direct molecular readout of toxin action. However to complete any mechanistic understanding of PFT behavior, this functional kinetic readout must be linked to the underlying changes in toxin structure, binding, conformation, or stoichiometry. Here we review how single-molecule imaging methods might be used to further our understanding of PFTs, and provide detailed practical guidance on the use of droplet interface bilayers as a method capable of examining both single-molecule fluorescence and single-channel electrical signals from PFTs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/articles/21/Parperis-methods</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/articles/21/Parperis-methods</guid>
        
        
        <category>papers</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lockdown Christmas</title>
        <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/group/LockdownChristmas.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;maincolumn-figure&quot;&gt;A Christmas break over lockdown in London.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/articles/21/LockdownChristmas</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/articles/21/LockdownChristmas</guid>
        
        <category>fun</category>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fast slow folding of an outer membrane porin</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;OMPGFRET&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;OMPGFRET&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/OMPG_folding.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Single-molecule FRET imaging of beta-barrel folding.&lt;/span&gt;
In comparison to globular proteins, the spontaneous folding and insertion of β-barrel membrane proteins is surprisingly slow, typically occurring on the order of minutes. Using single-molecule Förster Resonance Energy Transfer to report on the folding of fluorescently-labelled Outer Membrane Protein G we measured the real-time insertion of a β-barrel membrane protein from an unfolded state. Folding events were rare, and fast (&amp;lt;20 ms); occurring immediately upon arrival at the membrane. This combination of infrequent, but rare, folding resolves this apparent dichotomy between slow ensemble kinetics, and the typical timescales of biomolecular folding.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 25 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/articles/20/Weatherill-bioarxiv</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/articles/20/Weatherill-bioarxiv</guid>
        
        
        <category>papers</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Single molecule imaging of cholesterol-dependent cytolysin assembly</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;PFOSMF&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;PFOSMF&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/PFOSMF.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Tracking Perfingolysin O assembly and pore formation.&lt;/span&gt;
We exploit single-molecule tracking and optical single channel recording in droplet interface bilayers to resolve the assembly pathway of the Cholesterol-Dependent Cytolysin, Perfringolysin O. This enables quantification of the stoichiometry of PFO complexes during assembly with millisecond temporal resolution and 20 nanometre spatial precision. Our results support a model of overall stepwise irreversible assembly, dominated by monomer addition, but with infrequent assembly from larger partial complexes. Furthermore, our results suggest a dominant proportion of inserted, but non-conductive intermediates in assembly.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/articles/20/Senior_bioarxiv</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/articles/20/Senior_bioarxiv</guid>
        
        
        <category>papers</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Yujie Guo</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;YujieGuo&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;YujieGuo&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/people/yujie_mugshot.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Yujie Guo&lt;/span&gt;
Yujie joined the lab in 2019 as a PhD student as part of the King’s-China Scholarship Council PhD Scholarship programme. Her project uses iSCAT microscopy to understand polymerisation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/articles/19/YujieGuo</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/articles/19/YujieGuo</guid>
        
        
        <category>people</category>
        
        <category>current</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Artificial signal transduction across membranes</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;cbic2019-toc.jpg&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;cbic2019-toc.jpg&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/cbic2019-toc.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Artificial Signal Transduction across Membranes.&lt;/span&gt; A key conundrum in the construction of an artificial cell is to simultaneously maintain a robust physical barrier to the external environment, while also providing efficient exchange of information across this barrier. Biomimicry provides a number of avenues by which such requirements might be met. Herein, we provide a brief introduction to the challenges facing this field and explore progress to date.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/articles/19/Vanuytsel-ChemBioChem</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/articles/19/Vanuytsel-ChemBioChem</guid>
        
        
        <category>papers</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Modifying membrane morphology and interactions with DNA origami clathrin-mimic networks</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;DNAClathrin.jpg&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;DNAClathrin.jpg&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;fullwidth&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/DNAClathrin.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We designed a three-arm DNA origami nanostructure whose shape resembles that of the clathrin triskelion.&lt;/span&gt;
We describe the triggered assembly of a bioinspired DNA origami meshwork on a lipid membrane. DNA triskelia, three-armed DNA origami nanostructures inspired by the membrane-modifying protein clathrin, are bound to lipid mono- and bilayers using cholesterol anchors. Polymerization of triskelia, triggered by the addition of DNA staples, links triskelion arms to form a mesh. Using transmission electron microscopy, we observe nanoscale local deformation of a lipid monolayer induced by triskelion polymerization that is reminiscent of the formation of clathrin-coated pits. We also show that the polymerization of triskelia bound to lipid bilayers modifies interactions between them, inhibiting the formation of a synapse between giant unilamellar vesicles and a supported lipid bilayer.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/articles/19/Journot-ACSNano</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/articles/19/Journot-ACSNano</guid>
        
        
        <category>papers</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
