<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <description></description>
    <link>http://markwallace.org</link>
    <atom:link href="http://markwallace.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Hajra Basit</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/people/basit_mugshot_small.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image alt&quot; title=&quot;Hajra Basit&quot; /&gt;
Hajra joined the Wallace group in Oxford on a Marie Curie IE fellowship in July 2014. In her time in the Wallace group, she studied the twin-arginine transport system, both, in vivo and in vitro. She then obtained a John Fell fund in collaboration with Simon Newstead, to extend this work to studying other transporter proteins of the MFS type in artificial bilayers, using single-molecule FRET.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://markwallace.org/people/HajraBasit</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://markwallace.org/people/HajraBasit</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Christopher Parperis</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/people/Parperis_mugshot.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image alt&quot; title=&quot;Christopher Parperis&quot; /&gt;
Christopher joined the Wallace group in 2017. Working in collaboration with Oxford Nanopore Technologies his PhD research looks to examine the mechanism of DNA sensing in a protein nanopore.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://markwallace.org/people/ChristopherParperis</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://markwallace.org/people/ChristopherParperis</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Urea-Mediated Anomalous Diffusion in Supported Lipid Bilayers</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Diffusion in biological membranes is seldom simply Brownian motion; instead, the rate of diffusion is dependent on the timescale of observation and so is often described as anomalous. In order to help better understand this phenomenon, model systems are needed where the anomalous subdiffusion of the lipid bilayer can be tuned and quantified. We recently demonstrated one such model by controlling the excluded area fraction in supported lipid bilayers (SLBs) through the incorporation of lipids derivatised with polyethylene glycol. Here we extend this work, using urea to induce anomalous subdiffusion in SLBs. By tuning incubation time and urea concentration, we produce DCPC bilayers that exhibit anomalous behaviour on the same scale observed in biological membranes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://markwallace.org/papers/Weatherill_2018_ArXiv</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://markwallace.org/papers/Weatherill_2018_ArXiv</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lipid Bilayer Modulation using DNA Origami Mimics of Clathrin.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The assembly of clathrin coats on vesicles is a major endocytotic pathway, and the effects of clathrin’s structure on vesicle formation are still unclear. Here we exploit DNA origami nanostructures designed as structural mimics of clathrin. Using DNA clathrin mimics we seek to isolate the effects of shape and structure on membrane properties. DNA nanostructures associate with lipid membranes via cholesterol anchors and can be triggered to polymerise into a meshwork on the membrane. We explore how this origami network can be used to induce structural changes in giant unilamellar vesicles.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://markwallace.org/papers/Ramakrishna_2018_BiophysJ</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://markwallace.org/papers/Ramakrishna_2018_BiophysJ</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Dynamic tuneable G protein-coupled receptor monomer-dimer populations.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;G protein-coupled receptors (GPCRs) are the largest class of membrane receptors, playing a key role in the regulation of processes as varied as neurotransmission and immune response. Evidence for GPCR oligomerisation has been accumulating that challenges the idea that GPCRs function solely as monomeric receptors; however, GPCR oligomerisation remains controversial primarily due to the difficulties in comparing evidence from very different types of structural and dynamic data. Using a combination of single-molecule and ensemble FRET, double electron–electron resonance spectroscopy, and simulations, we show that dimerisation of the GPCR neurotensin receptor 1 is regulated by receptor density and is dynamically tuneable over the physiological range. We propose a “rolling dimer” interface model in which multiple dimer conformations co-exist and interconvert. These findings unite previous seemingly conflicting observations, provide a compelling mechanism for regulating receptor signalling, and act as a guide for future physiological studies.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://markwallace.org/papers/Dijkman_NatComms_2018</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://markwallace.org/papers/Dijkman_NatComms_2018</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>iSCAT Microscopy of Phase Separated Lipid Membranes.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Characterizing the lateral organization of lipid membranes is important for understanding the function of cell membranes. The most common way to determine miscibility phase behavior is using fluorescence microscopy, where the presence of separate phases is imaged by the preferential partitioning of a labeled lipid. However, fluorescence microscopy requires adding an additional lipid component, and can also lead to photooxidation. Interference scattering microscopy (iSCAT) is a label-free imaging technique that images the differences in light scattering from different regions of a sample. iSCAT is capable of imaging coexisting domains. We quantify the sensitivity of iSCAT to physical parameters including thickness mismatch, topography, and the presence of defects.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://markwallace.org/papers/Blosser_2018_BiophysJ</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://markwallace.org/papers/Blosser_2018_BiophysJ</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>PhD funding for 2018</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We’re looking for &lt;strong&gt;two new PhD researchers&lt;/strong&gt; for 2017/8 to work on vesicle self-replication, new tools for optical imaging, and nanopore sequencing. &lt;a href=&quot;mailto://mark.wallace@kcl.ac.uk&quot;&gt;Get in touch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://markwallace.org/2018/PhDadvert/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://markwallace.org/2018/PhDadvert/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>New PhD researchers</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Steven and Chris join the lab! Welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://markwallace.org/2017/WelcomePhDs/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://markwallace.org/2017/WelcomePhDs/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>PhD funding for 2017</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We’re looking for &lt;strong&gt;three new PhD researchers&lt;/strong&gt; for 2017/8 to work on vesicle self-replication, new tools for optical imaging, and nanopore sequencing. &lt;a href=&quot;mailto://mark.wallace@kcl.ac.uk&quot;&gt;Get in touch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://markwallace.org/2017/PhDadvert/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://markwallace.org/2017/PhDadvert/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Measuring the potential energy barrier to lipid bilayer electroporation.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Electroporation is a common tool for gene transfection, tumour ablation, sterilization and drug delivery. Using experimental methods, we explore the temperature dependence of electropore formation in a model membrane system (droplet-interface bilayers), using optical single-channel recording to image the real-time gating of individual electropores. We investigate the influence of the agarose substrate on electropores formed in this system. Furthermore, by examining the temperature-dependent kinetics of pore opening and closure we are able to estimate a barrier to pore opening in 1,2-diphytanoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphocholine (DPhPC) membranes to be 25.0 ± 8.3 kT, in agreement with previous predictions. Overall these measurements help support the toroidal model of membrane electroporation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of the themed issue ‘Membrane pores: from structure and assembly, to medicine and technology’.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://markwallace.org/papers/Sengel_2017_PhilTrans</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://markwallace.org/papers/Sengel_2017_PhilTrans</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
